[Waco] United Daughters of the Confederacy: Mary West Chapter records, Inclusive: 1866-1996, undated, Bulk: 1935-1977
Baylor University, The Texas Collection
[Waco] United Daughters of the Confederacy: Mary West Chapter records
Inclusive: 1866-1996, undated, Bulk: 1935-1977
Baylor University, The Texas Collection http://www.baylor.edu/lib/texas/
2321
Mary West Chapter #2381, United Daughters of the Confederacy
2 document boxes, 9 oversized boxes.
The [Waco] United Daughters of the Confederacy: Mary West Chapter records consist of manuscripts collected from 1866-1996. These papers contain correspondence, literary productions, financial papers, and scrapbook materials.
Administrative Information
Physical Description
General condition: Good.
Biography/Profile
Organized in 1896, the Waco chapter of the United Daughters of the Confederacy is still active in the local community. Originally the organization dedicated monuments, decorated graves, and lobbied for textbooks acceptable to their group in the early 1900s, similar to the activities of the United Confederate Veterans. Though the goals of the Daughters of the Confederacy have changed through the years as different generations have come and gone, they still seek to remember their version of the war through dedicating monuments, decorating graves, raising money, and many other activities.
Like many Daughters of the Confederacy chapters throughout the South, the Mary West Chapter was originally an auxiliary organization to the local Confederate veterans camp, the Pat Cleburne camp. Though the daughters’ group began in 1890, it did not choose to affiliate with the new United Daughters organization until 1896, when they became the third chartered group in the state.
The Waco chapter was named for Mary West, the founder and driving force behind the local group for many years. Despite the organization being re-chartered several times, most recently in 2004, Mary West’s name has always been attached to the group. It is thought that the reorganization of the group under several different charters explains some discrepancies in the chapter’s number through the years, as it has held the numbers 3, 26, and 2381.
The group wrote a constitution, held annual meetings and reunions, and participated in state and national reunions and events. It is not known where they originally met for meetings and socials, but by the 1930s they were meeting in an old log cabin in Cotton Palace Park in Waco. The cabin was moved in 1933 to Harrington Park close to Baylor University, and Baylor bought the property in 1947. The group was left without a place to meet after their cabin burned in 1959.
Though active well into the mid 1900s, at some point the charter for the Mary West group expired. Re-chartered in 2004, the group continues to promote Civil War heritage causes, and often works with the Waco Sons of Confederate Veterans chapter.
Scope and Content
The [Waco] United Daughters of the Confederacy: Mary West Chapter records begin in 1866 and ends in 1996. Records include correspondence, financial papers, literary productions, scrapbooks and scrapbook material, and other printed materials. An extensive collection of scrapbooks for the years 1972-1984 gives an excellent record for local Civil War heritage activities in the area, including the Waco Sons of Confederate Veterans Camp and the Mexia Confederate Reunion Grounds organization. Clippings throughout the collection give limited but vital information on Civil War remembrance activities in Waco, and the Mary West Daughters chapter in particular.
The scrapbooks in this collection give much information about the early years of the chapter, but most do not have dates or publishing information. The few that do have such information are from the Waco Tribune, so probably most are from that publication.
There are large gaps in the chronological history of this organization as preserved within this collection. It is assumed that many of the missing scrapbooks and documents that fit in those gaps are either still with the group or are housed in the United Daughters of the Confederacy
Collection, Texas Confederate Museum, Fort Worth, Texas.
Arrangement
The [Waco] United Daughters of the Confederacy: Mary West Chapter records is arranged in 4 series: I. Correspondence, II. Financial Documents, III. Literary Productions, IV. Scrapbooks and Scrapbook Materials.
The box numbering system is intended to sort the collection completely by date. Following the collection materials by box number is completely confusing, but the dates were used to sort the collection for easy retrieval of specific years for researchers.
All loose materials filed in folders from scrapbooks have the page number of the scrapbook that they came from in the upper right-hand corner of the paper.
Access Restrictions
All requests for copying of materials must be submitted to The Texas Collection in writing. Please use the Request Form for Copying Materials sheet. Unpublished materials authored or otherwise produced by the creator (s) of this collection are in the public domain. There are no restrictions on use. Copyright status for other collection materials is unknown. Transmission or reproduction of materials protected by U.S. Copyright Law (Title 17, U.S.C.) beyond that allowed by fair use requires the written permission of the copyright owners. Works not in the public domain cannot be commercially exploited without permission of the copyright owners. Responsibility for any use rests exclusively with the user.
Acquisition Information
Accession No. 2321. Acquired 1982-08-27
Related Resources
Items in related collections
[Waco] United Daughters of the Confederacy: Mary West Chapter records, Inclusive: 1866-1996, undated, Bulk: 1935-1977
Related references
Dayton Kelley, ed. The Handbook of Waco and McLennan County, Texas (Waco: Texian, 1972): 274.
“Mary West Chapter 26, United Daughters of the Confederacy, Waco, McLennan County, Texas.” Accessed 2011 August 12.
Morales, Monica. “Confederate Monument Honors Locals.” The Lariat. 1999 November 12.
Sims, Sterling. “Sims, Sterling [Vertical File] Term Paper.” Texas Collection, Baylor University.
Texas Historical Commission. “The Sims Cabin.” Texas Historic Sites Atlas, 1963. Accessed 2011 August 12.
Index Terms
Places
Confederate States of America -- History -- Societies, etc.; Texas -- History -- Civil War, 1861-1865 -- Societies, etc.; United States -- History -- Civil War, 1861-1865 -- Monuments.
Subjects
Literature -- Societies, etc.; Women -- Texas -- Waco -- Societies and clubs.
Genres
Clippings (Books, newspapers, etc.); Correspondence.; Essays.; Financial records.; Pamphlets.; Programs.; Scrapbooks.
- Correspondence, 1949-1950, undated; 1
  Administrative Information
  Physical Description
  General condition: Unknown.
  Biography/Profile
  The series includes two ledgers and associated loose materials. These papers contain notes on dues and organization expenses.
  - General, 1949-1950 (Box 1, Folder 1)
- Financial Documents, 1866-1936, undated; 2
  - Ledger 1, 1909-1912 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Ledger 1: Loose Materials, 1866-1909, undated (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Ledger 2, 1935-1936 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Loose Materials, 1936 (Box 1, Folder 5)
- Literary Productions, 1906-1980, undated; 3
  The series includes pamphlets, essays, programs, reports, and clippings. Most of the pamphlets were produced by the Mary West Chapter, while most of the programs were produced by the National United Daughters of the Confederacy organization. Clippings include both local and national news on the organization.
  - Essays, 1923, undated (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Milady’s Own Book, undated (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Pamphlets: General, 1914-1927, undated (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Pamphlets: West Camp, 1972-1974 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Pamphlets: West Camp, 1974-1976 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Pamphlets: West Camp, 1976-1978 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Programs: General, 1933-1980, undated (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Programs: National Convention, 1935-1936 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Programs: National Convention, 1938 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Programs: State Convention, 1906-1941 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Reports: National, 1928-1935 (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Reports: National, 1936 (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Clippings, 1946-1960, undated (Box 1, Folder 18)
- Scrapbooks and Scrapbook Material, 1892-1996, undated; 4
  This series includes scrapbooks and loose material from scrapbooks. These scrapbooks seem to be in complete runs during the years 1931-1944, 1972-1984, and then 1994-1996. The early and undated scrapbooks contain much information of the time period not related directly to the Daughters, or even to the Civil War. Most of the dated scrapbooks after 1940 are exclusively about the local chapter, and contain many photographs and unique items for their specific year.
  - Scrapbook 1, 1892-1905 (Box 3 OVZ, Folder 1)
  - Scrapbook 1: Loose Materials, 1892-1905 (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - Scrapbook 2, 1931-1932 (Box 3 OVZ, Folder 2)
  - Scrapbook 2: Loose Materials, 1931-1932 (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - Scrapbook 3, 1932-1934 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Scrapbook 3: Loose Materials (1 of 2), 1932-1934 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Scrapbook 3: Loose Materials (2 of 2), 1932-1934 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Scrapbook 4, 1938 (Box 5 OVZ, Folder 1)
  - Scrapbook 4: Loose Materials, undated (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Scrapbook 5, 1934-1944 (Box 5 OVZ, Folder 2)
  - Scrapbook 5: Loose Materials (1 of 9), 1934-1944 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Scrapbook 5: Loose Materials (2 of 9), 1934-1944 (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Scrapbook 5: Loose Materials (3 of 9), 1934-1944 (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Scrapbook 5: Loose Materials (4 of 9), 1934-1944 (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Scrapbook 5: Loose Materials (5 of 9), 1934-1944 (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - Scrapbook 5: Loose Materials (6 of 9), 1934-1944 (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - Scrapbook 5: Loose Materials (7 of 9), 1934-1944 (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - Scrapbook 5: Loose Materials (8 of 9), 1934-1944 (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - Scrapbook 5: Loose Materials (9 of 9), 1934-1944 (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - Scrapbook 5: Loose Materials: Artifacts, 1940, undated (Box 2, Folder 14)
  - Scrapbook 6, 1972-1973 (Box 7 OVZ)
  - Scrapbook 7, 1973-1974 (Box 7 OVZ)
  - Scrapbook 8, 1974-1975 (Box 4 OVZ, Folder 3)
  - Scrapbook 8: Loose Materials, 1974-1975 (Box 2, Folder 15)
  - Scrapbook 9, 1975-1976 (Box 8 OVZ, Folder 1)
  - Scrapbook 9: Loose Materials, 1975-1976 (Box 2, Folder 16)
  - Scrapbook 10, 1976-1977 (Box 8 OVZ, Folder 2)
  - Scrapbook 10: Loose Materials, 1976-1977 (Box 2, Folder 17)
  - Scrapbook 11, 1977-1978 (Box 9 OVZ, Folder 1)
  - Scrapbook 12, 1978-1979 (Box 9 OVZ, Folder 2)
  - Scrapbook 13, 1979-1980 (Box 10 OVZ, Folder 1)
  - Scrapbook 13: Loose Materials, 1979-1980 (Box 2, Folder 18)
  - Scrapbook 14, 1980-1981 (Box 10 OVZ, Folder 2)
  - Scrapbook 15, 1981-1982 (Box 11 OVZ, Folder 1)
  - Scrapbook 16, 1983-1984 (Box 11 OVZ, Folder 2)
  - Scrapbook 17, 1990-1991 (Box 4 OVZ, Folder 1)
  - Scrapbook 18, 1994-1996 (Box 12 OVZ, Folder 1)
  - Scrapbook 18: Loose Materials, 1994-1996 (Box 13 OVZ, Folder 1)
  - Scrapbook 19, undated (Box 4 OVZ, Folder 3)
  - Scrapbook 19: Loose Materials (1 of 2), undated (Box 13 OVZ, Folder 2)
  - Scrapbook 19: Loose Materials (2 of 2), undated (Box 13 OVZ, Folder 3)
  - Scrapbook 20 (1 of 3), undated (Box 13 OVZ, Folder 4)
  - Scrapbook 20 (2 of 3), undated (Box 13 OVZ, Folder 5)
  - Scrapbook 20 (3 of 3), undated (Box 13 OVZ, Folder 6)